<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Anmol Sarma</title>
    <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Anmol Sarma</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-in</language>
    <copyright>Except where noted otherwise, content licensed under a &lt;a href=&#39;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#39;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2017 11:56:27 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anmolsarma.in/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk @ RFC&#39;s We Love: CoAPing with the Internet of Things</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/coap-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2017 11:56:27 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/coap-talk/</guid>
      <description>Gave an introductory talk on CoAP at the 5th RFC&amp;rsquo;s We Love meetup. Turnout was low, probably owing to the rains and the festive season. It was still fun and had great discussions.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DCCP: The socket type you probably never heard of</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/dccp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 23:10:50 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/dccp/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR: DCCP is a relatively newer transport layer protocol which draws from both TCP and UDP. Jump straight to the example C code.
Background Historically, the majority of the traffic on the Internet has been over TCP which provides a reliable connection-oriented stream between two hosts. UDP has been mainly used by applications whose brief transfers would be unacceptably slowed by TCP&amp;rsquo;s connection establishment overhead or those for which timeliness is more important than reliability.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Books I Read in 2015</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/books-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 21:36:15 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/books-2015/</guid>
      <description>India After Gandhi by Ramachandra Guha A thoroughly sourced, brilliantly written and mostly objective history of India. Guha’s scholarship and unbiased account really shines throughout the book. Save for one non-sequitur and one inaccurate and one might say unfair characterization there is nothing to complain about. The rare photographs included in the book are fascinating by themselves. Reading the book makes you wonder if it is Indian history itself or Guha’s writing that makes it such a page turner.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lazy Performance Comparison of WordPress and Ghost</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/lazy-performance-comparison-of-wordpress-and-ghost/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2015 18:40:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/lazy-performance-comparison-of-wordpress-and-ghost/</guid>
      <description>So, I switched to a new blogging platform. Again. After trying out a static approach, I moved back to a WordPress when I stumbled across OpenShift (And their fantastic free plan). That was well over two years ago. In the meantime, I hardly blogged and didn&amp;rsquo;t really run into any issues but the blog did feel a tad sluggish.
Fast-forward to yesterday when I had a sudden impulse to try something new.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Art of Living Foundation&#39;s Kurshed Batliwala Debunked</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/kurshed-batliwala-debunked/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2013 10:07:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/kurshed-batliwala-debunked/</guid>
      <description>A critical look at Khurshed Batliwala’s talk, “Technology of Spirituality” delivered at Ruia College, Mumbai.
  Mr. Batliwala makes a number of extraordinary claims about the state of ancient Indian science and technology. Most of them however, turn out to be exaggerations, misinterpretations or outright fabrications. He then attributes all scientific progress to ‘spirituality’.
The talk is nothing more than a sales pitch for Mr. Mr. Ravi Shankar’s ‘Art of Living Foundation’.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk @ EmWare: Getting started with Linux</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/talk-emware/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 06:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/talk-emware/</guid>
      <description>Gave an introductory talk on Linux, basically a rehash of the talk I gave at KLU a couple of years ago.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk @ EmWare: Getting Started with Git</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/talk-emware-getting-started-with-git/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2013 06:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/talk-emware-getting-started-with-git/</guid>
      <description>Gave an introductory interactive tutorial on using Git. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t finish the slides on time but managed cover everything on the agenda.
Now that the talk is done, I&amp;rsquo;m don&amp;rsquo;t feel especially inclined to complete the slides.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defeating India&#39;s Central Monitoring System</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/defeating-the-central-monitoring-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2013 14:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/defeating-the-central-monitoring-system/</guid>
      <description>The Government of India has rolled out the Central Monitoring System which will allow it to access any piece of data passing through an Indian service provider. This means the government can now read all your text messages, emails and call records.
Because privacy does not bring in votes, it is highly unlikely that any political party will oppose this system. Circumventing this system however, is rather simple using PGP or any other munition grade cryptographic scheme.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello Again, World!</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/hello-again-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Feb 2013 17:59:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/hello-again-world/</guid>
      <description>Here it goes again: After a couple of attempts with Blogger, a dozen iterations with WordPress, a very brief tryst with Drupal and a false start with Bloggart, I’ve now decided to ditch dynamic content management systems and give Octopress a spin.
I like the idea of a statically generated site I can deploy anywhere. I used Sphinx for a documentation once and the experience with was pretty good. However, getting Sphinx to work for a personal blog seemed to be too much work, so Octopress it is.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Das Blinkenlights on the MSP430 Launchpad with Linux</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/msp430-launchpad-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2013 19:06:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/msp430-launchpad-linux/</guid>
      <description>TI’s MSP430 LaunchPad development kit offers some serious bang for the buck. You get two modern 16-bit microcontrollers, a programmer-cum-debugger with pins broken out and a USB cable for less than 5 USD inclusive of shipping. TI even provides two free (as in beer) IDE’s for Windows. Linux support though was a bit sketchy when the board was first released.
Things of course have greatly improved and getting the Launchpad to work with Linux is now a breeze.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mole Nama: A Linux Fantasy Saga</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/mole-nama-a-linux-fantasy-saga/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Aug 2012 18:23:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/mole-nama-a-linux-fantasy-saga/</guid>
      <description>Mole Nama
A historical account of the Mole’ani people in the Free Lands
 -Inestimabel Montcastellus
  We Mole’ani are a Geekic people, who like millions of other races call the Free Lands home. However, our people originally came from the other side; the Dark Lands that shall not be named. The Dark Lands were under monopolistic rule of the Borg and their brethren. Piracy was common and so were the viral diseases which accompanied the booty.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk @ KLU: Linux? Say whaat?!</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/talk-klu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2011 21:20:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/talk-klu/</guid>
      <description>Gave an introductory talk on Linux at Koneru Lakshmiah University, with Vamsifollowing up with a talk on Bugs and Hacks as a part of the ‘workshop’ organised by the KLU Linux Users Group. With about 150 newbish students in attendance, it was fun albeit in a masochistic kind of a way.
Here’s a shitty picture from the talk, courtesy of Vamsi:
And here are the sildes: Edit: I lost the slides.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hello, World!</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/hello-world-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2011 17:57:01 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/hello-world-2/</guid>
      <description>This is the 11th iteration of my blog/homepage. I’ve finally found a setup that I like (Thanks to Bloggart!) and unless I run into any major issues, I’m probably going to stick with it. Maybe now I’ll finally stop resetting the site and get down to actually blogging!
Watch this space!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/about/</guid>
      <description>Anmol Sarma is a network protocol engineer living it up in Bengaluru, India. When not referring to himself in the third person, he breaks stuff, writes code and knows things. Sometimes, he makes CG art. He also has a blog.
Drop him a line on: me@anmolsarma.in</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Renders</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/renders/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/renders/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>