<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Open Letter on Anmol Sarma</title>
    <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/tags/open-letter/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Open Letter on Anmol Sarma</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-in</language>
    <copyright>Except where otherwise noted, content on this website is licensed under a &lt;a href=&#39;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#39;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://www.anmolsarma.in/tags/open-letter/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>An Open Letter to Dr. Subramanian Swamy</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/an-open-letter-to-dr-subramanian-swamy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2014 06:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/an-open-letter-to-dr-subramanian-swamy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Dr. Subramanian Swamy,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This in reference to the below picture shared by the page run by ShankhNaad in your name. Please allow me to address this latest instance of imbecility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your contention that industrial and vehicular pollution is considered &amp;lsquo;No problem&amp;rsquo; can only result from a mind boggling level of cognitive dissonance or a mala fide intention to mislead. There is a reason why factories have to get an environmental clearance and vehicles have to meet Bharat Stage emission norms. Everyone agrees that pollution from them is a big enough problem to have an explicit legal framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laws aside, I find it incredulous that you pretend that there have never been protests against pollution caused due to factories and power plants. Perhaps you choose to ignore them because they were lead by &amp;lsquo;leftists&amp;rsquo;. Then again, you would surely have come across campaigns promoting public transport and cycling in a bid to reduce vehicular pollution but choosing to ignore them allows you to build up your straw man argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As for your relative comparison of other sources which according to you “produces much much more deadly pollution”, pray tell us, which of those leads to direct exposure to heavy metals, free radicals, perchlorates and other assorted carcinogens? And this is to say nothing of the unrelenting, deafeningly loud noise all of it in the middle of densely populated areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lets not pretend this is actually an issue of religion or tradition. The people of Ayodhya certainly would not have welcomed back their beloved prince with clouds of asthma inducing smoke. Nor would anyone until relatively recently have had access to chemicals to blow up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you insist using the Dhimmi label, I have to ask: Your own party colleague, Dr. Harsh Vardhan, the Union Minister for Health and Family Welfare, made an appeal for a &amp;lsquo;Silent Diwali&amp;rsquo;. Does that make him a Dhimmi too? Or is he simply a “leftists pseudo-intellectual”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.anmolsarma.in/images/2015/04/Diwali-Shank-Naad.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Note: The above image belongs to a third party and is used in accordance with Section 52 of the Indian Copyright Act of 1957.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Open Letter to Chetan Bhagat</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/an-open-letter-to-chetan-bhagat/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2014 06:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/an-open-letter-to-chetan-bhagat/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Mr. Chetan Bhagat,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have never been a fan of your cutesy novels targeted at clueless young adults. However, I am extremely disturbed by your attempts to &amp;lsquo;enlighten&amp;rsquo; your readership by projecting your partisan views as the neutral and objective voice of reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The major chunk of your fan base is made up of people who have little to no understanding of political issues and they tend to treat your half assed political ramblings as gospel. As undeserved as it may be, you wield considerable influence over a certain niche of the Indian youth. I urge you to use this power responsibly for the greater good and stop propping up disgraced politicos with a vested interest in perpetuating the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You frequently talk about systemic change and revolution, it is about time you walked the talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best Wishes,&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Open Letter to Devyani Khobragade</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/an/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2014 06:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/an/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Miss Khobragade,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government and the people of India were on your side when the issues were international law and diplomatic protocol. Now that you are back in India, you are requested to stop playing the martyr. You see, nobody gives a rodent&amp;rsquo;s posterior if you cannot visit your sons should they choose to study and work in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best wishes,&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Open Letter to Modibots</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/an-open-letter-to-modibots/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 06:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/an-open-letter-to-modibots/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dear Modibots,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the Internet, spammers are considered the scum of humanity. By indiscriminately spamming people&amp;rsquo;s inboxes, you are only giving credence to the idea that you are a bunch of obnoxiously ignorant boisterous knuckle-dragging sheeple who do not belong in the civilized world, let alone the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best wishes,&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>