<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tech on Anmol Sarma</title>
    <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/tags/tech/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tech on Anmol Sarma</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-in</language>
    <copyright>Except where noted otherwise, content licensed under a &lt;a href=&#39;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#39;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 23:10:50 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anmolsarma.in/tags/tech/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>DCCP: The socket type you probably never heard of</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/dccp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 23:10:50 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/dccp/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR: DCCP is a relatively newer transport layer protocol which draws from both TCP and UDP. Jump straight to the example C code.
Background Historically, the majority of the traffic on the Internet has been over TCP which provides a reliable connection-oriented stream between two hosts. UDP has been mainly used by applications whose brief transfers would be unacceptably slowed by TCP&amp;rsquo;s connection establishment overhead or those for which timeliness is more important than reliability.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lazy Performance Comparison of WordPress and Ghost</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/lazy-performance-comparison-of-wordpress-and-ghost/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Apr 2015 18:40:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/lazy-performance-comparison-of-wordpress-and-ghost/</guid>
      <description>So, I switched to a new blogging platform. Again. After trying out a static approach, I moved back to a WordPress when I stumbled across OpenShift (And their fantastic free plan). That was well over two years ago. In the meantime, I hardly blogged and didn&amp;rsquo;t really run into any issues but the blog did feel a tad sluggish.
Fast-forward to yesterday when I had a sudden impulse to try something new.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk @ EmWare</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/talk-emware/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 May 2013 06:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/talk-emware/</guid>
      <description>Gave an introductory talk on Linux, basically a rehash of the talk I gave at KLU a couple of years ago.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk @ EmWare: Getting Started with Git</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/talk-emware-getting-started-with-git/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 May 2013 06:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/talk-emware-getting-started-with-git/</guid>
      <description>Gave an introductory interactive tutorial on using Git. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t finish the slides on time but managed cover everything on the agenda.
Now that the talk is done, I&amp;rsquo;m don&amp;rsquo;t feel especially inclined to complete the slides.
 </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defeating India&#39;s Central Monitoring System</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/defeating-the-central-monitoring-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2013 14:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/defeating-the-central-monitoring-system/</guid>
      <description>The Government of India has rolled out the Central Monitoring System which will allow it to access any piece of data passing through an Indian service provider. This means the government can now read all your text messages, emails and call records.
Because privacy does not bring in votes, it is highly unlikely that any political party will oppose this system. Circumventing this system however, is rather simple using PGP or any other munition grade cryptographic scheme.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Das Blinkenlights on the MSP430 Launchpad with Linux</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/msp430-launchpad-linux/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Jan 2013 19:06:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/msp430-launchpad-linux/</guid>
      <description>TI’s MSP430 LaunchPad development kit offers some serious bang for the buck. You get two modern 16-bit microcontrollers, a programmer-cum-debugger with pins broken out and a USB cable for less than 5 USD inclusive of shipping. TI even provides two free (as in beer) IDE’s for Windows. Linux support though was a bit sketchy when the board was first released.
Things of course have greatly improved and getting the Launchpad to work with Linux is now a breeze.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talk @ KLU</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/talk-klu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2011 21:20:38 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/talk-klu/</guid>
      <description>Gave an introductory talk on Linux at Koneru Lakshmiah University, with Vamsifollowing up with a talk on Bugs and Hacks as a part of the ‘workshop’ organised by the KLU Linux Users Group. With about 150 newbish students in attendance, it was fun albeit in a masochistic kind of a way.
Here’s a shitty picture from the talk, courtesy of Vamsi:
And here are the sildes:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>