<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Politics on Anmol Sarma</title>
    <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/tags/politics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Politics on Anmol Sarma</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-in</language>
    <copyright>Except where noted otherwise, content licensed under a &lt;a href=&#39;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/&#39;&gt;Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License&lt;/a&gt;.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2014 06:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.anmolsarma.in/tags/politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>An Open Letter to Dr. Subramanian Swamy</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/an-open-letter-to-dr-subramanian-swamy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2014 06:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/an-open-letter-to-dr-subramanian-swamy/</guid>
      <description>Dear Dr. Subramanian Swamy,
This in reference to the below picture shared by the page run by ShankhNaad in your name. Please allow me to address this latest instance of imbecility.
Your contention that industrial and vehicular pollution is considered &amp;lsquo;No problem&amp;rsquo; can only result from a mind boggling level of cognitive dissonance or a mala fide intention to mislead. There is a reason why factories have to get an environmental clearance and vehicles have to meet Bharat Stage emission norms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Open Letter to Chetan Bhagat</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/an-open-letter-to-chetan-bhagat/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2014 06:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/an-open-letter-to-chetan-bhagat/</guid>
      <description>Dear Mr. Chetan Bhagat,
I have never been a fan of your cutesy novels targeted at clueless young adults. However, I am extremely disturbed by your attempts to &amp;lsquo;enlighten&amp;rsquo; your readership by projecting your partisan views as the neutral and objective voice of reason.
The major chunk of your fan base is made up of people who have little to no understanding of political issues and they tend to treat your half assed political ramblings as gospel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Open Letter to Devyani Khobragade</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/an/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Jan 2014 06:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/an/</guid>
      <description>Dear Miss Khobragade,
The government and the people of India were on your side when the issues were international law and diplomatic protocol. Now that you are back in India, you are requested to stop playing the martyr. You see, nobody gives a rodent&amp;rsquo;s posterior if you cannot visit your sons should they choose to study and work in the US.
Best wishes,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An Open Letter to Modibots</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/an-open-letter-to-modibots/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 06:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/an-open-letter-to-modibots/</guid>
      <description>Dear Modibots,
On the Internet, spammers are considered the scum of humanity. By indiscriminately spamming people&amp;rsquo;s inboxes, you are only giving credence to the idea that you are a bunch of obnoxiously ignorant boisterous knuckle-dragging sheeple who do not belong in the civilized world, let alone the Internet.
Best wishes,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Defeating India&#39;s Central Monitoring System</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/defeating-the-central-monitoring-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2013 14:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/defeating-the-central-monitoring-system/</guid>
      <description>The Government of India has rolled out the Central Monitoring System which will allow it to access any piece of data passing through an Indian service provider. This means the government can now read all your text messages, emails and call records.
Because privacy does not bring in votes, it is highly unlikely that any political party will oppose this system. Circumventing this system however, is rather simple using PGP or any other munition grade cryptographic scheme.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hindutva and Fascism Compared</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/hindutva-and-fascism-compared/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Sep 2012 19:20:11 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/hindutva-and-fascism-compared/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>