<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>books on Anmol Sarma</title>
    <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/tags/books/</link>
    
    <language>en-in</language>
    
    
    <atom:link href="https://www.anmolsarma.in/tags/books/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Books I Read in 2018</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/books-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2019 23:41:22 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/books-2018/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-information-a-history-a-theory-a-flood-by-james-gleick&#34;&gt;The Information: A History, a Theory, a Flood by James Gleick&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eclectic, engrossing and thoroughly enjoyable. From Ada Lovelace and Charles Babbage to Maxwell and Einstein to Shanon and Turing: Gleick&amp;rsquo;s masterful prose captures both the ideas and personalities of the men and women who made the world what it is today. Apart from the lucid explanation of the foundations of information theory, the book is packed full of fascinating historical accounts. To top it off is the brilliant synthesis and narrative. Would highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-white-tiger-by-aravind-adiga&#34;&gt;The White Tiger by Aravind Adiga&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A parable new India relating individuality&amp;rsquo;s struggle for freedom from the societal forces of class and caste that seek to imprison it. The narrative while being deeply allegorical is at the same time raw, visceral and credulous. Devoid of any idealistic or ideological pretensions, the story of Balram Halwai&amp;rsquo;s rise paints a wholly unflattering yet undeniably accurate picture of modern India. Would highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;masters-of-doom-by-david-kushner&#34;&gt;Masters of Doom by David Kushner&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A gushing homage from a DOOM fanboy meant for other video game fanboys. While the detailed technical discussions of early games are interesting, the book&amp;rsquo;s focus is on the behind the scenes drama between John Carmack and John Romero. An inordinate amount of prose is spent on trite character profiles which makes parts of the book an absolute chore to read. Would not recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;artemis-by-andy-weir&#34;&gt;Artemis by Andy Weir&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like &lt;em&gt;The Martian&lt;/em&gt; but on the moon and with added criminal intrigue. The action-packed plot is complemented by charming and extremely likeable characters. While the science is solid the writing is anything but. The mostly unambitious dialogue turns wince-inducing in places. Overall, a quick and enjoyable read. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;an-era-of-darkness-by-shashi-tharoor&#34;&gt;An Era of Darkness by Shashi Tharoor&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on Tharoor&amp;rsquo;s virally popular Oxford Union debate, &lt;em&gt;An Era of Darkness&lt;/em&gt; is a breathless polemic about the horrors of British rule in India. While the book does not offer anything new &amp;ndash; something that the preface readily admits, it does offer a cogent rebuttal to revived colonial apologism. The work is assuredly nationalistic, not of a narrow, parochial or exclusionary sort but of the staunchly liberal, self-assured and inclusive variety. That being said, the book does feel a bit longer than necessary. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-girl-with-the-dragon-tattoo-by-stieg-larsson-as-translated-by-reg-keeland&#34;&gt;The Girl with the Dragon Tattoo by Stieg Larsson as translated by Reg Keeland&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A slightly atypical murder mystery potboiler. The storyline while not entirely bad is chock full of genre cliches and the translated prose isn&amp;rsquo;t exactly exciting. The drawn-out novel is only redeemed by the character of Lisbeth Salander, the eponymous girl with the dragon tattoo. An entertaining read but not a particularly memorable one. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;flash-boys-by-michael-lewis&#34;&gt;Flash Boys by Michael Lewis&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part misguided hit piece on High Frequency Trading, part hagiography of Brad Katsuyama and part native advertisement for the IEX stock exchange: &lt;em&gt;Flash Boys&lt;/em&gt; is utterly without merit. Michel Lewis valiantly tries to project large institutional investors as heroic victims while repeatedly making the absurd claim that the markets are rigged. Even putting the bias aside, the book could be cut down to a long-form article while conveying exactly the same amount of information. Would not recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;flowers-for-algernon-by-daniel-keyes&#34;&gt;Flowers for Algernon by Daniel Keyes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A heart-wrenching science fiction tale that confronts the accepted notions of intelligence, humanity, love and kindness. Written as a series of progress reports by the protagonist Charlie Gordon as he experiences the full cycle of effects of an experimental cognitive enhancement operation. The journey is captivating and ultimately heartbreaking. Would highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;surely-youre-joking-mr-feynman-by-richard-feynman&#34;&gt;Surely You&amp;rsquo;re Joking, Mr. Feynman! by Richard Feynman&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A collection of anecdotes and reminisces from the life of Richard Feynmanmann. While on the whole very amusing, the tone of the stories tends to be rather self-congratulatory with some episodes definitely stretching credulity. But it is a worthy read with the very last chapter, Cargo Cult Science deserving a special mention. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-old-man-and-the-sea-by-ernest-hemingway&#34;&gt;The Old Man and the Sea by Ernest Hemingway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;True to its name almost the entirety of the novel is an account of a conspicuously unlucky old man and his struggle with the sea and its creatures. While it is over-romanticized to the point of unrealism, Hemmingway manages to capture the majestic force of nature, the raw physicality of a fisherman&amp;rsquo;s life and above all the indomitable force of the human spirit. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;countdown-to-zero-day-by-kim-zetter&#34;&gt;Countdown to Zero Day by Kim Zetter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A thoroughly journalistic account of the Stuxnet worm. Tightly written and technically sound, it focusses mostly on the heroic efforts of security researchers who discovered and reverse engineered the worm. The technical exposition is lucid with just the right amount of detail. No liberties are taken with mundane facts to craft a biased or misleading narrative. The geopolitics and circumstances surrounding Stuxnet too are dealt from a neutral perspective without the speculative hysteria that seems to permeate most cybersecurity reporting. Would highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-ministry-of-utmost-happiness-by-arundhati-roy&#34;&gt;The Ministry of Utmost Happiness by Arundhati Roy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A somewhat underwhelming comeback novel from Arundhati Roy after a gap of more than two decades. The sprawling plot line is unfolded mostly by telling and not by showing. And while Roy can effortlessly make the reader look where she wants, it&amp;rsquo;s not entirely clear as to what she wants us to see. In the hands of a lesser writer, such faults would have spelt doom but in Roy more than redeems the novel with her masterful prose. However, the perspective in some places is confusing and politics are inserted into the narrative with all the subtlety of a sledgehammer. While it&amp;rsquo;s no &lt;em&gt;God of Small Things&lt;/em&gt;, it makes for a decent read. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;factfulness-by--hans-rosling-ola-rosling-and-anna-rosling-rönnlund&#34;&gt;Factfulness by  Hans Rosling, Ola Rosling and Anna Rosling Rönnlund&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Combating outdated perceptions, misleading generalizations and meaningless labels in the search for truth, &lt;em&gt;Factfulness&lt;/em&gt; is hands down the best book I&amp;rsquo;ve read in 2018. Measuredly staying away from hysteria, &lt;em&gt;Factfulness&lt;/em&gt; makes the case that not only is the world becoming a better place but also that the threat of overpopulation is overblown. The book provides a framework for better understanding of the world and offers specific advice on how to avoid being misled by information. Would highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dune-by-frank-herbert&#34;&gt;Dune by Frank Herbert&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An undeniable classic of science fiction, &lt;em&gt;Dune&lt;/em&gt; at its surface is about an interplanetary blood feud. But beyond the seemingly trite premise is a vivid account of a weird and wonderful world with a very unique zoology.  The world building with its myriad cultures is absolutely stellar, the political intrigue is captivating and the character dynamics are powerfully evocative. The only weakness of the novel is the tendency to use long winding speeches to explain the plot points. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;bad-blood-by-john-carreyrou&#34;&gt;Bad Blood by John Carreyrou&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The riveting tale of the spectacular rise and epic fall of Silicon Valley&amp;rsquo;s Blood Unicorn. A behind-the-scenes account of how John Carreyrou&amp;rsquo;s explosive pieces in the Wall Street Journal came to be, &lt;em&gt;Bad Blood&lt;/em&gt; combines journalistic prowess with narrative flair. The lurid details of the puffery, duplicity and manipulation behind Theranos&amp;rsquo;s eye-watering valuation make for a satisfying sense of schadenfreude. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sacred-games-by-vikram-chandra&#34;&gt;Sacred Games by Vikram Chandra&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A story about a washed up gangster, a cynical cop and the city of Mumbai in peril. The main plot flows at a meandering pace while drawing in a staggering number of tributaries. And frankly, the tributaries are far more interesting. The sense of impending doom never really hits home and everything is a bit too well done. Too much time is spent on the protagonist&amp;rsquo;s backstory which is entirely uninteresting. The dialogue while interlaced with vernacular vocabulary simply does not carry any emotional force. At over 700 pages, the book just isn&amp;rsquo;t worth the effort. The Netflix show, while significantly different from the source material, is a much better proposition. Would not recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;born-a-crime-by-trevor-noah&#34;&gt;Born a Crime by Trevor Noah&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A collection of stories from Trever Noah&amp;rsquo;s youth while growing up in of post-Apartheid South Africa. Yhe book is not meant to be a comprehensive treatise of that tumultuous period but a personal account of how it was to live through it all. The writing is both insightful and extremely humorous. Naturally, it deals with issues of racism, poverty and crime: But despite its heavy subject matter, it is a very pleasant read. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;tinker-tailor-soldier-spy-by-john-le-carré&#34;&gt;Tinker Tailor Soldier Spy by John le Carré&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A dense novel with a convoluted plot and way too many named characters making cameos. The pacing is unsettlingly uneven and there are no sympathetic characters. The supposedly accurate jargon-laced description of spycraft makes for extremely dull reading. Would not recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;red-plenty-by-francis-spufford&#34;&gt;Red Plenty by Francis Spufford&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Soviet Union was founded on a dream. The talk about establishing the dictatorship of the proletariat was mostly bluster. The real dream was optimizing production by means of central planning. Such a system, it was presumed would avoid the inherent inefficiencies of the market.  Red Plenty is a genre-bending collection of vivid short stories that capture life under such a planned economy in all its triumphs and absurdities. While none of the stories is true, the details that back them are all very much real. Would highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-colour-of-magic-by-terry-pratchett&#34;&gt;The Colour of Magic by Terry Pratchett&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An absurdist fantasy featuring an incompetent wizard. While the book definitely has its moments of brilliant humour, they feel few and far between. The world and the characters have a lot of potential which I am told is realized to full effect in the later &lt;em&gt;Discworld&lt;/em&gt; novels. Sadly, in &lt;em&gt;The Color of Magic&lt;/em&gt; though, Terry Prachet is yet to find his voice. Would not recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;thinking-fast-and-slow-by-daniel-kahneman&#34;&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow by Daniel Kahneman&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really should have been subtitled &lt;em&gt;The Ludic Fallacy Run Amok&lt;/em&gt;. A collection of studies and anecdotal stories all around a central theme, suitably vulgarized for general consumption. Filled with grand generalisations based on dubious conclusions from small under-powered behavioural experiments. Much ado is made about the so-called &lt;em&gt;Priming Effect&lt;/em&gt; which has since been thoroughly been debunked. The central premise of there being two distinct modes of thinking is asserted with no evidence. One this the book does prove is that behavioural economics &amp;ndash;that bastard child of psychology &amp;ndash; is built on an edifice of fashionable nonsense. Would not recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-handmaids-tale-by-margaret-atwood&#34;&gt;The Handmaid&amp;rsquo;s Tale by Margaret Atwood&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A speculative dystopian novel set in a deeply patriarchal world taken over by religious fundamentalists. The protagonist is a woman called &amp;lsquo;Offred&amp;rsquo;, her name signifying her status as a possession &amp;lsquo;of Fred&amp;rsquo;. Extremely well written, the book features a double narrative, with one chronicling the fall of the old order and the other dealing with life under the new. The intimate prose and visceral detail make reading The Handmaid&amp;rsquo;s Tale an almost physical experience. Would highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;mans-search-for-meaning-by-viktor-frankl&#34;&gt;Man&amp;rsquo;s Search for Meaning by Viktor Frankl&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Literal survivorship bias taken to the absolute extreme. Frankl devises an entire theory of psychotherapy backed by the fact that he survived a concentration camp when so many others perished. The narrative deceptively suggests that Frankl spent months in the Auschwitz death camp when in reality he spent most of his time as a prisoner in the Dachau labour camp. Also conveniently left out are details about Frankl&amp;rsquo;s unqualified experiments with lobotomy on his fellow prisoners. Would not recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;em-and-the-big-hoom-by-jerry-pinto&#34;&gt;Em and the Big Hoom by Jerry Pinto&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A moving tragicomic family drama centred around the bipolar manic-depressive mother Em. The story feels too authentic to not be true. While it does not intend to be a commentary on the state of mental health care in India, the parts that deal with it are heartbreaking. Despite the melancholy setting, the dialogue is equal parts brilliant and funny. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-inner-game-of-tennis-by-timothy-gallwey&#34;&gt;The Inner Game of Tennis by Timothy Gallwey&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 161 pages it might seem short but is in fact 160 pages too long. It boldly claims its advice isn&amp;rsquo;t applicable just to tennis but to all endeavours of life. While I can&amp;rsquo;t speak about its applicability to tennis, I did not find absolutely anything of value in the book which for the most part is trite and repetitive. Would not recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;lord-of-the-flies-by-william-golding&#34;&gt;Lord of the Flies by William Golding&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On its surface, a Robinsonade featuring a group of schoolboys. But on a deeper level an allegorical commentary on civilization, the basis of cooperation and the memetic power of belief. While the premise is compelling enough, the characters are not particularly well developed, with each of them neatly fitting into an archetype for plot convenience. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-road-to-wigan-pier-by-george-orwell&#34;&gt;The Road to Wigan Pier by George Orwell&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A Sociological investigation leading to an impassioned polemic. The first part is made up of Orwell&amp;rsquo;s journalistic reportage from his journey through the depressed areas of North England in the midst of the Great Depression. From the lives of miners to housing shortages to the sheer ugliness of industrial towns, Orwell&amp;rsquo;s writing is detailed, vivid and ultimately deeply disturbing. The second has Orwell playing the devil&amp;rsquo;s advocate pointing out the hypocrisies, pettiness and crankiness exhibited by self-avowed Socialists of the champagne drinking variety. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;poonachi-or-the-story-of-a-black-goat-by-perumal-murugan-as-translated-by-n-kalyan-raman&#34;&gt;Poonachi: Or the Story of a Black Goat by Perumal Murugan as translated by N Kalyan Raman&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A brilliant political commentary dressed-up as a fable about a black goat. The story masterfully captures the trials and tribulations of life in an Indian village. Rich in allegory, Perumal Murugan captures the rebelliousness of the proletarian spirit. The spirit, however, is broken by the material deprivation and authoritarian subjugation that serve as the backdrop for a story that is fundamentally about love and tenderness. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-we-sleep-by-matthew-walker&#34;&gt;Why We Sleep by Matthew Walker&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A  scholarly explanation of &lt;em&gt;Why We Sleep&lt;/em&gt; and an impassioned plea for &lt;em&gt;Why We Should Be Sleeping A Lot More Than We Currently Do&lt;/em&gt;. Be it improving cognitive performance, physical endurance, attractiveness or general well being, Dr Walker&amp;rsquo;s scientific remedy for everything is ensuring that one regularly gets 8 hours of sleep. He goes so far as to say that there is no human physiological process that is not improved by sufficient sleep. The book has more potential to be life changing that any self-help book out there, provided the sound advice is actually adhered to. The pithy takeaway being: &lt;em&gt;Sacrificing sleep does not make you hardworking or successful, it makes you fat and stupid.&lt;/em&gt; Would highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ghachar-ghochar-by-vivek-shanbhag-as-translated-by-srinath-perur&#34;&gt;Ghachar Ghochar by Vivek Shanbhag as translated by Srinath Perur&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A psychological drama about a dysfunctional family that is tangled up beyond repair. While the philosophical musings of the narrator make for amusing reading, the crux of the novel is the sequence of seemingly meaningless events and actions which capture the characters&amp;rsquo; state of mind. There isn&amp;rsquo;t a larger overarching theme apart from the possibility of money complicating and changing the dynamics of human relationships. The novel is more of an exploration rather than an explanation. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Books I Read in 2017</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/books-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2018 20:28:40 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/books-2017/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-god-of-small-things-by-arundhati-roy&#34;&gt;The God of Small Things by Arundhati Roy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A beautifully heart-rending exploration of the human condition. The prose is almost lyrical and the narrative is dreamlike and completely immersing. All the little details add up to symbolise something bigger. The book is part political satire, part social commentary part psychological drama and part fairy tale. In the midst of all this, it manages to capture the thought process of children like no other book.  Would highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-win-friends-and-influence-people-by-dale-carnegie&#34;&gt;How To Win Friends And Influence People by Dale Carnegie&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original &amp;ldquo;self-help&amp;rdquo; book. Carnegie offers solid advice for dealing with business relationships and public speaking. While some of it may be obvious, it’s especially useful for introverts and people with social anxiety because it outlines a few simple techniques that make meeting new people a little easier. However, some of the techniques for conflict resolution come across as outright manipulative. I doubt it will be life-changing but if you&amp;rsquo;re going to read a self-help book, you could certainly do a lot worse than &lt;em&gt;How to Win Friends&lt;/em&gt;. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-martian-by-andy-weir&#34;&gt;The Martian by Andy Weir&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the movie was great, the book is just so much better. A gripping page-turner with a focus on realism and scientific accuracy. Anyone even remotely interested in science and technology would find an immensely relatable hero in Mark Watney. To top off the exciting plot, the writing is crisp, the pacing perfect and the dialogue is brilliant and funny. Would highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;restart-the-last-chance-for-the-indian-economy-by-mihir-sharma&#34;&gt;Restart: The last chance for the Indian Economy by Mihir Sharma&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A blunt, irreverent and acerbic account of the long list of policy blunders which ail India&amp;rsquo;s economy. Probably the most well stated and researched rant you&amp;rsquo;ll ever read. The book is filled with anecdotes that are both insightful and funny. While Mihir Sharma jumps the gun with his suggestion in a few places, the work makes it absolutely clear that he knows what he&amp;rsquo;s talking about. He also breaks from the tradition of lionising India&amp;rsquo;s IT and pharma industries and calls them out for what they are. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-curious-incident-of-the-dog-in-the-night-time-by-mark-haddon&#34;&gt;The Curious Incident of the Dog in the Night-Time by Mark Haddon&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A touching and poignant account of an autistic savant&amp;rsquo;s attempt to solve mysteries. The book does a wonderful job of capturing the perspective of someone with a thoroughly logical mind and difficulties interacting with other people. It also manages to convey the frustrations of those who care for children with special needs.  An excellent if psychologically dissociating read. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-emperor-of-all-maladies-by-siddhartha-mukherjee&#34;&gt;The Emperor of All Maladies by Siddhartha Mukherjee&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A biography of cancer punctuated with the experiences of the author as a practising oncologist. A perfect blend of scientific exposition and dramatic narrative. The vivid descriptions of biological processes are accessible and the metaphors absolutely exemplary. Also included is a history of the propaganda war waged by tobacco companies and cancer researchers. If you were unaware of the state of contemporary cancer treatments, it will leave you a lot more informed but possibly also a bit worried. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;midnights-children-by-salman-rushdie&#34;&gt;Midnight&amp;rsquo;s Children by Salman Rushdie&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A story that willfully defies description. Notionally about 1001 children whose destinies are magically intertwined with that of independent India. A narrative packed with digressions, deliberate false steps and allegorical insinuations coupled with immensely funny and brilliant prose. The book captures the essence of everyday Indian life with both the magnificent and the squalid. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;sapiens-a-brief-history-of-humankind-by-yuval-noah-harari&#34;&gt;Sapiens: A Brief History of Humankind by Yuval Noah Harari&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like Guns, Germs and Steel but even grander. The sort of book that completely changes one&amp;rsquo;s perspective. The book is full of big ideas ranging from the power of collective delusions, the relationship between wheat and humans and the deep unconscious effects of advertising. Hands down the best book I read in 2017. Would highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;norse-mythology-by-neil-gaiman&#34;&gt;Norse Mythology by Neil Gaiman&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A short but gripping and suspenseful retelling of the foundational myths of the Norse pantheon; stories of how Odin, Thor and Loki came to be and how they would fall. The prose is full of witticisms and frequently blurs the distinction between metaphor and reality. Overall, a delightful read. Would Recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-selfish-gene-by-richard-dawkins&#34;&gt;The Selfish Gene by Richard Dawkins&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An immensely readable treatise on the gene-centred view of evolution by the high priest of New Atheism. The title really does the book injustice, it deals as much with the altruism of individuals as it does with the selfishness of genes. Dawkins also introduces the concept of a meme: a unit for human cultural evolution. Would highly recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fahrenheit-451-by-ray-bradbury&#34;&gt;Fahrenheit 451 by Ray Bradbury&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A dystopian novel about a future where books are outlawed and firemen burn any that are found. It can be read both as a criticism of censorship as well as that of mass media. Perhaps the second theme is more relevant today in the age of viral media than it was in Bradbury&amp;rsquo;s time. While a good read overall, the prose does come off as a bit snobbish. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;black-swan-by-nassim-taleb&#34;&gt;Black Swan by Nassim Taleb&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An annoyingly long-winded, insufferably pompous and thoroughly grating account of the disproportionate effects of unforeseen events. Much of the book reads like a self-aggrandizing rant. While there are a few good ideas in the book, it could have easily been cut to a third of its size without losing anything of value. Skip the book and listen to one of Taleb&amp;rsquo;s lecture instead. Would not recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;foucaults-pendulum-by-umberto-eco-as-translated-by-william-weaver&#34;&gt;Foucault&amp;rsquo;s Pendulum by Umberto Eco as translated by William Weaver&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Described as The Thinking Man&amp;rsquo;s Da Vinci Code, it&amp;rsquo;s a satirical exposition of people&amp;rsquo;s desire to believe their own version of the truth. Chock full of allusions and references, and incredibly dense, it certainly is not an easy or light read. The plot and characters are hilarious and the writing extremely clever. Reading this, one might end up feeling mentally inadequate. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-raj-at-war-by-yasmin-khan&#34;&gt;The Raj at War by Yasmin Khan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Subtitled A People’s History of India’s Second World War, Yasmin Khan does an excellent job collating the experiences of ordinary Indians caught up in the war. There are accounts of not just soldiers but also lascars, nurses, labourers and peasants. The horrors of the Bengal famine are captured in all its gory detail. Also shown is the birth of India&amp;rsquo;s all-powerful and hopelessly apathetic babudom and the police state. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;snow-crash-by-neal-stephenson&#34;&gt;Snow Crash by Neal Stephenson&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An absurdist, dystopian science fiction novel dealing with elements of history, linguistics, anthropology, religion, computer science, politics, cryptography, memetics and philosophy. Primarily, the plot revolves around information and how it affects humans. The difference between the workings of a man (Or for that matter, a beast) and a machine is frequently blurred to great effect. The book also popularised the term avatar meaning a virtual persona. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;deep-work-by-cal-newport&#34;&gt;Deep Work by Cal Newport&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The subtitle, Rules for Focused Success in a Distracted World is a definite oversell. It starts off decently. The premise of modern work environments that prioritize superficial and immediate metrics over creating actual value is spot on, as is the description of viral social media platforms stealing our attention and our ability to focus. The meat of the book though, the rules are the usual self-help claptrap full of anecdotes with a dash of survivorship bias. Nevertheless, the initial part of the book makes for good reading. Some might even find the rules useful. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-clockwork-orange-by-anthony-burgess&#34;&gt;A Clockwork Orange by Anthony Burgess&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An unabashedly dark and satirical take on the morality of free will.  The many depictions of violence carry a sense of excitement from Alex, the central character but, the book does not in any way promote violence. Large parts of the book are written in a fictional Russian influence slang which feels very natural while not harming intelligibility. The writing has an almost lyrical quality to it, especially when describing music. A short but unsettling read. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Books I Read in 2015</title>
      <link>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/books-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jan 2016 21:36:15 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.anmolsarma.in/post/books-2015/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.anmolsarma.in/images/2016/books-2015.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;india-after-gandhi-by-ramachandra-guha&#34;&gt;India After Gandhi by Ramachandra Guha&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A thoroughly sourced, brilliantly written and mostly objective history of India. Guha’s scholarship and unbiased account really shines throughout the book. Save for one non-sequitur and one inaccurate and one might say unfair characterization there is nothing to complain about. The rare photographs included in the book are fascinating by themselves. Reading the book makes you wonder if it is Indian history itself or Guha’s writing that makes it such a page turner. Definitely the best book I’ve read this year. Would  recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;patriots-and-partisans-by-ramachandra-guha&#34;&gt;Patriots and Partisans by Ramachandra Guha&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A collection of essays on India from a self proclaimed liberal centrist. Chock full of telling anecdotes and witty insights.  While it is interesting on it’s own, it is nowhere as gripping as India After Gandhi. Guha is definitely a better scholar than he is a polemicist but he really excels as a storyteller. The chapter describing how the Congress Dynasty and its sychophants destroyed an insititution Guha personally cherished was probably the best of the lot. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ramayana-by-valmiki-as-retold-by-c-rajagopalachari&#34;&gt;Ramayana by Valmiki as retold by C. Rajagopalachari&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A highly condensed and simplified retelling of the timeless epic from one &lt;em&gt;bhakta&lt;/em&gt; intended for prospective young &lt;em&gt;bhaktas&lt;/em&gt;. But for me, Rajaji’s commentary and comparison between different versions of the epic are more interesting than the actual narrative. The standard trope of digressing to heap praise on the protagonist slackens the pace and gets rather irritating after the first few times. So irritating that finishing this book took me far longer than it should have, given its size. Would not recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;picture-of-dorian-grey-by-oscar-wilde&#34;&gt;Picture of Dorian Grey by Oscar Wilde&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beneath the endlessly quotable characters and beyond the absurd supernatural premise lies a much deeper message. Or possibly several such messages. Sadly, I for one have no idea what they are supposed to be. Wilde’s self-indulgent prose aside, I found the book incredibly difficult to read and had to force myself to finish it. Unlike almost everyone else I know who has read the book, it had no discernible impact on me except for making me a little more choosy about what I read. Would not recommend&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-short-history-of-nearly-everything-by-bill-bryson&#34;&gt;A Short History Of Nearly Everything by Bill Bryson&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very lucid and easily digestible survey of what we know and how we know what we know. Funny, insightful and entertaining, Bryson’s curiosity and style makes even geology seem interesting. While doing a good job of explaining the science and the history behind the science, it also manages to capture the human side of the countless passionate men and women who dedicate their lives to advancing the state of human knowledge. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-ultimate-hitchhikers-guide-to-the-galaxy-by-douglas-adams&#34;&gt;The Ultimate Hitchhiker&amp;rsquo;s Guide to the Galaxy by Douglas Adams&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technically not one book but &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;a trilogy of five&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;. The Hitchhiker&amp;rsquo;s Guide to the Galaxy and The Restaurant at the End of the Universe are absolutely hilarious. Life, the Universe and Everything, So Long, and Thanks for All the Fish and Mostly Harmless are slightly less so. It&amp;rsquo;s probably a bad idea to go through all of them in one go because the absurdity gets a little too much to handle. An otherwise brilliant collection. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;siddhartha-by-hermann-hesse-as-translated-by-hilda-rosner&#34;&gt;Siddhartha by Hermann Hesse as translated by Hilda Rosner&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best thing about this book is its size. At barely 150 pages, you don’t waste too much time on this New Age twaddle full of knowing smiles, hearts spontaneously bursting with joy and characters who for some reason resemble various fruit and vegetables. Much like the narrative, Hesse’s attempt at reproducing Sanskrit idioms feels jarring and pointless.  The only realization I had from reading this book was that the eponymous protagonist went about the ashramas of life in a vipareeta order. Would not recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;train-to-pakistan-by-khushwant-singh&#34;&gt;Train to Pakistan by Khushwant Singh&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fictional account of a very real disaster. Kushwant Singh’s prose is simple, engaging and very readable. The characters  and the setting feel all too familiar and real as do the norms and social memes. The book does a very good job of capturing the senselessness of the violence and the tribal rationalizations invoked to justify it. The ending, while a little over the top, does manage to leave an emotional impact. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;if-its-monday-it-must-be-madurai-by-srinath-perur&#34;&gt;If It&amp;rsquo;s Monday It Must Be Madurai by Srinath Perur&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first travel book I’ve ever read and it did not disappoint. Perur’s book is as much about the people he traveled with and their reasons  for travelling as it is bout the places themselves. The observations of the stereotypical Indian traits and notions are spot on and the commentary is effortlessly funny. The book is perhaps more accurately subtitled A Conducted tour of the Indian Traveler. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;brave-new-world-by-aldous-huxley&#34;&gt;Brave New World by Aldous Huxley&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book most frequently compared to and contrasted with George Orwell’s dystopian 1984. Huxley’s  take on dystopia is an anti-utopia centered around the cult of Henry Ford. While the premise is decent, the over the top caricature of Fordian society as the opposite of what is Huxley’s sense of morality does reduce the overall impact and the result is no where as haunting as 1984’s Big Brother. The book is short enough to finish in a couple of sittings and it is probably best to finish it quickly as I found it difficult to read when stretched out. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-accidental-prime-minister-by-sanjaya-baru&#34;&gt;The Accidental Prime Minister by Sanjaya Baru&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the 2008 financial crisis, as major economies of the world went into recession, the Indian growth story seemed to remain intact. International journalists looking for post hoc explanation began to hail Dr. Manmohan Singh as the economist prime minister who held it together. Unblemished by the taint of corruption that was to follow, at this point Dr. Singh enjoyed international recognition and renown. In this supposed tell-all book, Sanjaya Baru claims credit for the successful PR campaign he undertook as the PM’s spin doctor. While book is in no way a revelation, it does flesh out the details and put things into perspective about how the UPA government and the Congress party functioned. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;arthashastra-by-kautilya-as-translated-and-rearranged-by-ln-rangarajan&#34;&gt;Arthashastra by Kautilya as translated and rearranged by L.N. Rangarajan&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As if taking a cue from the success of Art of War themed self-help books, distilled Kautilyan teachings re-purposed for the modern corporate have become popular of late. Not wanting to be given truisms of some random author’s reading into Kautilya, I went to the original source. While I couldn’t find any universally applicable ancient wisdom, reading the Arthashastra was enjoyable. Rather than the simplified, whitewashed and sometimes politically colored descriptions of ancient India of history books, the Arthashastra is a contemporary insider’s account of ancient Indian society or at least an idealized conception of it. But given its nature, the book is filled with lists and tables and permutations and gradations. Skimming through these and focusing on more subjective descriptions makes for a very interesting reading. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;burmese-days-by-george-orwell&#34;&gt;Burmese Days by George Orwell&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on Orwell’s time as an officer of the Indian Imperial Police, Burmese Days pulls no punches while describing the colonial experience. The hypocrisy and cognitive dissonance of the British, the opportunism and corruption of native officials, the vanity and the pointless pursuit of prestige by everyone involved, the frustrated attempts at finding love an companionship and finally the frailty of the human condition, Orwell tackles it all. While nowhere near as popular as Orwell’s other books, Burmese Days is certainly an excellent book. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;who-was-shivaji-by-govind-pansare&#34;&gt;Who Was Shivaji by Govind Pansare&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was not meant to be a book. Expanded from an earlier speech, Who Was Shivaji would have remained a niche political pamphlet hadn’t Govind Pansare been murdered in cold blood. The comrades of Left World Books seemed to have no ethical or ideological qualms about exploiting the death of its author. Even when printed using the ridiculously large font, the book still doesn’t reach a hundred pages. There just isn&amp;rsquo;t enough material to justify turning into a book. As for the material that is there, it is mostly unremarkable stuff. The most interesting parts of the book were actually the letters written by Shivaji, reproduced in the appendix. By far, the most disappointing book of the year. Would not recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-great-indian-novel-by-shashi-tharoor&#34;&gt;The Great Indian Novel by Shashi Tharoor&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Puns, allusions and witticisms that&amp;rsquo;s what The Great Indian Novel is made of. The title being a reference to Mahabharata, Sashi Tharoor’s debut novel tells the story of modern India using characters from the epic. Tharoor’s style is engaging, extremely irreverent and incredibly funny. Taking shots at everyone from Gandhi to Nehru to the Indian media with a few self-referential jokes about NRI’s and diplomats thrown in for good measure. After an excellent start, and buildup, the plot sags a bit. Given the subject matter, there probably is no closure possible but the climax does feel a bit week. Overall a decent way to close the year. Would recommend.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
